<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-01-27T12:22:51+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">mx-blog</title><subtitle>A blog about anything I find interesting foor a week or two, then forget about.  Written to the best of my ability and knowledge. For corrections, comments, interesting content please write an e-mail.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Thoughts on engineered sub-cultures</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2022/01/23/cult-or-culture.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Thoughts on engineered sub-cultures" /><published>2022-01-23T21:42:05+01:00</published><updated>2022-01-23T21:42:05+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2022/01/23/cult-or-culture</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2022/01/23/cult-or-culture.html">&lt;p&gt;In 2006 I temporarily joined a cult. I was 10. It was the FIFA world cup. And the cult was trading football stickers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Calling it a cult might seem overly dramatic, but everyone who has made a similar experience as a kid would not deny that the desire to collect the stickers and fill a complete album with them was overwhelming. It was also a social phenomenon: Stickers were traded, bet and even stolen, and many kids spend what seemed then like a fortune to buy more. We formed a frenzied, irrational subculture frowned apon by society at large; in other words a cult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the world cup went on, I formed a collecting group with my brother and a friend. We pooled our resources to fill a complete sticker album. The theory was that if we bought enough stickers - they were sold in packs of 10 for a small amount - we would eventually, through sheer luck and trading, be able to find one instance of each of the 200 odd stickers needed to fill the album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out not to work. After jointly purchsing over 600 stickers the album was not nearly complete while we owned 16 instances of an American player called Clint Dempsey. While this can be explained by probability theory, which of course we knew nothing about, no one in school seemed to have the stickers we needed either. But there was an abundance of Clint Dempsey et al.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/clint_dempsey.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Clint freaking Dempsey&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Clint freaking Dempsey&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solution to the mystery was of course that the company making the stickers was not producing the same quantity of each, as our parents explained to us in a patronizing tone. But we didn’t really care. We soon figured out which stickers were the rare ones and concentrated our efforts on those. The buying, trading, betting and stealing intensified. Kids with rare stickers or more complete albums were rewarded with attention, social status even. Some poorer and more ingenious kids even produced counterfeit stickers. But to no avail. The world cup ran its course. The sticker economy crashed. We quit the cult. The sticker album still remains unfinished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I no longer collect football stickers but the method is everywhere, from skins in multiplayer games to NFTs (Non-Fungible Tokens). There is a strange mixture of free market pricing mechanisms and human social hierarchical behaviour at play. It is imposed scarcity where there could be abundance. And people are hooked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this article I want to explore the concept of artificial scarcity in classical economics, and where we can find it traditionally. I then want to analyse how post-modern forms of artificial scarcity differ. Finally, I want to understand &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; they work. Are millions of people irrational or is there a rational justification for their behaviour? Is it an excess of capitalism? A fault in our culture? Is it inevitable, or even justifiable?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-is-a-culture&quot;&gt;What is a culture&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;–&amp;gt; Human organisation principle 
Shared values, social programming, collective action
Anchored in individual by social needs
Cultural programming promotes long-term cooperation
Cultural projects can be realized across generations
religion&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;–&amp;gt; Levels of organization
Tribe, city-state, nation-state&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;–&amp;gt; cult
subculture, short-term, non-sustainable&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-is-artificial-scarcity&quot;&gt;What is artificial scarcity?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In classical economics, artifical scarcity describes a situation, in which an economic good’s supply is restricted artificially. This means less of a good is produced than would actually be possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reasons for this can be vary. If a single company controls the totality of the supply of, say, oil, the company might, in order to maximize its profits, produce less oil then it can produce to increase the oil price. We would call this a monopoly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other cases society artificially bestows monopolies to encourage a certain behaviour: The patent system was designed to make inventors monopolists over their invention. The owner of a patent may, for a period of 20 years, exclusively decide by whom and under which conditions their invention may be used. Rational inventors, of course, maximize their profits and thereby reduce supply of the invention. We bestow this privilege to inventors to encourage invention in the first place. (If the system as it currently exists, fulfills this purpose well is unclear, but assumed here as a simplification.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An extreme example of artificial scarcity is intellectual property. The distribution of a piece of information incurs essentially no marginal cost. Software, media, ideas and other non-physical things share this characteristic. We still give creators full control over their creation, with similar effects as with patents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All these instances of artificial scarcity have in common that they reduce overall prosperity in the sense of classical economics. If fewer people can receive a good then could if supply was not artificially constrained, welfare is reduced. An example of this would be a newly invented cure not being available for all sufferers of the disease. Economists call this inefficiency in the market ‘deadweight loss’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Classical economists would thus agree that a situation of artificial scarcity needs to be justified by an overriding public interest, such as fostering innovation is in the case of patents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All examples of ‘classical’ artificial scarcity have a few characteristics in common:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;They necessarily require a monopoly (or something of a similar nature, such as a cartel) to be implemented. Otherwise individual economic actors (or coordinated groups of actors) do not have the ability to influence supply. If there are 100 companies producing shoes (perfectly substitutable shoes for now), a single company increasing their prices over the market price will not lead to higher profits for them but increase their competitors profits.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The economic goods in question actually increases welfare. An example would be oil for heating, medicine for curing a disease or software to manage information. If the economic goods where actually economic bads, artificial scarcity would of course be benefitial to welfare. An example of this is the supply of certain addictive drugs, which is highly restricted through legislation.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The supply of the economic good to one market participant does not influence the welfare for any other market participant. I do not become more or less sick if someone else’s sickness is treated with medicine. Of course, if someone else gets more medicine than they need and I get less than I need, overall welfare is reduced. This is called a suboptimal distribution. But an &lt;em&gt;additional&lt;/em&gt; unit of medicine supply cannot reduce welfare already provided by other units.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-has-changed&quot;&gt;What has changed?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can also see these factors in the soccer card example. Or can we?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is obviously a monopoly. FIFA has licensed the rights to print official world cup stickers to the company producing these stickers, thus they are free to set prices and supply as they wish. Since supply is limited for a few of the full set of stickers and stickers are sold in random batches the price of a full set of stickers rises due to the constrained supply. There is some obfuscation of this limit by the bundling and randomness, but even as kids we were aware of these tricks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second characteristic seems to hold too. Collecting stickers is fun. Opening a new pack of stickers is fun. Trading and betting them is fun. Achieving a complete set is fun. The welfare impact of football stickers must be positive. Or is it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first glance, the third characterisic is shared as well. The more full sets of stickers are produced, the more complete sticker albums, the happier the kids trying to complete an album, right? But what about the attention, the social status associated with owning rare stickers, the betting and trading and collecting. Would it still be as fun if one could achieve a full set with way less effort? Or even buy a full set for the few euros it costs to produce? Arguably not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems thus that the artificial rarity of some cards constituted their value in the first place. In contrast to classical artificial scarcity, the economic good (rare cards, social status, attention) is only an economic good in contrast to an economic bad (abundant cards, being excluded, being ignored). The game is zero-sum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the abundance of Clint Dempsey and friends ensured that the cards were established as a commodity among as many market participants as possible. It was not by accident that, in the weeks leading up to the world cup, you got a free pack of stickers when shopping for groceries or buying a comic book. The sticker album, too, was very cheap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The football world cup itself was also important. Football and patriotism formed a cultural foundation for the value of the cards. They were cheap stickers after all. What was printed on refered to deep cultural value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So not only was there artificial scarcity, but also artificial excess. There was a real, significant cultural event which gave the stickers relevance. All three were necessary to create artificial winners (kids with rare cards) and losers (kids with abundant cards). What resulted was quite real: There was a real market facilitating trade, real gambling and real criminal activity. The losers of course could improve their status by further investing time and money, thereby increasing the stickers cultural significance. A real hierarchy established itself. The game became and end in itself, a cult. A commercialized cult, that is, since the company which created it made millions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is post-modern artificial scarcity. It is a combination of classical artificial scarcity with cultural exploits to create commercial cults, zero-sum games for members from which rents are extracted. Let’s look in detail at how it works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-football-sticker-cult-and-other-examples&quot;&gt;The football sticker cult and other examples&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commercial 
–&amp;gt; detail of cult functioning 
–&amp;gt; FIFA-&amp;gt;cult? culture? commerzialization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cult-or-culture&quot;&gt;Cult or culture?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;–&amp;gt; culture –&amp;gt; long term, non-zero sum. 
–&amp;gt; cult –&amp;gt; short term, zero sum
–&amp;gt; there are monetary incentives to highjack culture and create cults 
–&amp;gt; culture is essential; people in need of culture are vulnerable to cults&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;–&amp;gt; cultural damages
–&amp;gt; economic damages
–&amp;gt; culture must be protected an actively formed to serve non-zero sum long-term growht and wellbeing&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html">In 2006 I temporarily joined a cult. I was 10. It was the FIFA world cup. And the cult was trading football stickers. Calling it a cult might seem overly dramatic, but everyone who has made a similar experience as a kid would not deny that the desire to collect the stickers and fill a complete album with them was overwhelming. It was also a social phenomenon: Stickers were traded, bet and even stolen, and many kids spend what seemed then like a fortune to buy more. We formed a frenzied, irrational subculture frowned apon by society at large; in other words a cult. As the world cup went on, I formed a collecting group with my brother and a friend. We pooled our resources to fill a complete sticker album. The theory was that if we bought enough stickers - they were sold in packs of 10 for a small amount - we would eventually, through sheer luck and trading, be able to find one instance of each of the 200 odd stickers needed to fill the album. It turned out not to work. After jointly purchsing over 600 stickers the album was not nearly complete while we owned 16 instances of an American player called Clint Dempsey. While this can be explained by probability theory, which of course we knew nothing about, no one in school seemed to have the stickers we needed either. But there was an abundance of Clint Dempsey et al. Clint freaking Dempsey The solution to the mystery was of course that the company making the stickers was not producing the same quantity of each, as our parents explained to us in a patronizing tone. But we didn’t really care. We soon figured out which stickers were the rare ones and concentrated our efforts on those. The buying, trading, betting and stealing intensified. Kids with rare stickers or more complete albums were rewarded with attention, social status even. Some poorer and more ingenious kids even produced counterfeit stickers. But to no avail. The world cup ran its course. The sticker economy crashed. We quit the cult. The sticker album still remains unfinished. I no longer collect football stickers but the method is everywhere, from skins in multiplayer games to NFTs (Non-Fungible Tokens). There is a strange mixture of free market pricing mechanisms and human social hierarchical behaviour at play. It is imposed scarcity where there could be abundance. And people are hooked. In this article I want to explore the concept of artificial scarcity in classical economics, and where we can find it traditionally. I then want to analyse how post-modern forms of artificial scarcity differ. Finally, I want to understand why they work. Are millions of people irrational or is there a rational justification for their behaviour? Is it an excess of capitalism? A fault in our culture? Is it inevitable, or even justifiable? What is a culture –&amp;gt; Human organisation principle Shared values, social programming, collective action Anchored in individual by social needs Cultural programming promotes long-term cooperation Cultural projects can be realized across generations religion –&amp;gt; Levels of organization Tribe, city-state, nation-state –&amp;gt; cult subculture, short-term, non-sustainable What is artificial scarcity? In classical economics, artifical scarcity describes a situation, in which an economic good’s supply is restricted artificially. This means less of a good is produced than would actually be possible. The reasons for this can be vary. If a single company controls the totality of the supply of, say, oil, the company might, in order to maximize its profits, produce less oil then it can produce to increase the oil price. We would call this a monopoly. In other cases society artificially bestows monopolies to encourage a certain behaviour: The patent system was designed to make inventors monopolists over their invention. The owner of a patent may, for a period of 20 years, exclusively decide by whom and under which conditions their invention may be used. Rational inventors, of course, maximize their profits and thereby reduce supply of the invention. We bestow this privilege to inventors to encourage invention in the first place. (If the system as it currently exists, fulfills this purpose well is unclear, but assumed here as a simplification.) An extreme example of artificial scarcity is intellectual property. The distribution of a piece of information incurs essentially no marginal cost. Software, media, ideas and other non-physical things share this characteristic. We still give creators full control over their creation, with similar effects as with patents. All these instances of artificial scarcity have in common that they reduce overall prosperity in the sense of classical economics. If fewer people can receive a good then could if supply was not artificially constrained, welfare is reduced. An example of this would be a newly invented cure not being available for all sufferers of the disease. Economists call this inefficiency in the market ‘deadweight loss’. Classical economists would thus agree that a situation of artificial scarcity needs to be justified by an overriding public interest, such as fostering innovation is in the case of patents. All examples of ‘classical’ artificial scarcity have a few characteristics in common: They necessarily require a monopoly (or something of a similar nature, such as a cartel) to be implemented. Otherwise individual economic actors (or coordinated groups of actors) do not have the ability to influence supply. If there are 100 companies producing shoes (perfectly substitutable shoes for now), a single company increasing their prices over the market price will not lead to higher profits for them but increase their competitors profits. The economic goods in question actually increases welfare. An example would be oil for heating, medicine for curing a disease or software to manage information. If the economic goods where actually economic bads, artificial scarcity would of course be benefitial to welfare. An example of this is the supply of certain addictive drugs, which is highly restricted through legislation. The supply of the economic good to one market participant does not influence the welfare for any other market participant. I do not become more or less sick if someone else’s sickness is treated with medicine. Of course, if someone else gets more medicine than they need and I get less than I need, overall welfare is reduced. This is called a suboptimal distribution. But an additional unit of medicine supply cannot reduce welfare already provided by other units. What has changed? We can also see these factors in the soccer card example. Or can we? There is obviously a monopoly. FIFA has licensed the rights to print official world cup stickers to the company producing these stickers, thus they are free to set prices and supply as they wish. Since supply is limited for a few of the full set of stickers and stickers are sold in random batches the price of a full set of stickers rises due to the constrained supply. There is some obfuscation of this limit by the bundling and randomness, but even as kids we were aware of these tricks. The second characteristic seems to hold too. Collecting stickers is fun. Opening a new pack of stickers is fun. Trading and betting them is fun. Achieving a complete set is fun. The welfare impact of football stickers must be positive. Or is it? At first glance, the third characterisic is shared as well. The more full sets of stickers are produced, the more complete sticker albums, the happier the kids trying to complete an album, right? But what about the attention, the social status associated with owning rare stickers, the betting and trading and collecting. Would it still be as fun if one could achieve a full set with way less effort? Or even buy a full set for the few euros it costs to produce? Arguably not. It seems thus that the artificial rarity of some cards constituted their value in the first place. In contrast to classical artificial scarcity, the economic good (rare cards, social status, attention) is only an economic good in contrast to an economic bad (abundant cards, being excluded, being ignored). The game is zero-sum. Furthermore, the abundance of Clint Dempsey and friends ensured that the cards were established as a commodity among as many market participants as possible. It was not by accident that, in the weeks leading up to the world cup, you got a free pack of stickers when shopping for groceries or buying a comic book. The sticker album, too, was very cheap. The football world cup itself was also important. Football and patriotism formed a cultural foundation for the value of the cards. They were cheap stickers after all. What was printed on refered to deep cultural value. So not only was there artificial scarcity, but also artificial excess. There was a real, significant cultural event which gave the stickers relevance. All three were necessary to create artificial winners (kids with rare cards) and losers (kids with abundant cards). What resulted was quite real: There was a real market facilitating trade, real gambling and real criminal activity. The losers of course could improve their status by further investing time and money, thereby increasing the stickers cultural significance. A real hierarchy established itself. The game became and end in itself, a cult. A commercialized cult, that is, since the company which created it made millions. This is post-modern artificial scarcity. It is a combination of classical artificial scarcity with cultural exploits to create commercial cults, zero-sum games for members from which rents are extracted. Let’s look in detail at how it works. The football sticker cult and other examples Commercial –&amp;gt; detail of cult functioning –&amp;gt; FIFA-&amp;gt;cult? culture? commerzialization. Cult or culture? –&amp;gt; culture –&amp;gt; long term, non-zero sum. –&amp;gt; cult –&amp;gt; short term, zero sum –&amp;gt; there are monetary incentives to highjack culture and create cults –&amp;gt; culture is essential; people in need of culture are vulnerable to cults –&amp;gt; cultural damages –&amp;gt; economic damages –&amp;gt; culture must be protected an actively formed to serve non-zero sum long-term growht and wellbeing</summary></entry></feed>